<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications and Research | Aurélien Sallin</title>
    <link>https://asallin.github.io/publication/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://asallin.github.io/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Publications and Research</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 Aurelien Sallin</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://asallin.github.io/media/icon_hufb0af0ffa7c4769e88338e6608699541_8962_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Publications and Research</title>
      <link>https://asallin.github.io/publication/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Missing stars: Gender differences in giftedness assessments</title>
      <link>https://asallin.github.io/publication/gifted_referral/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asallin.github.io/publication/gifted_referral/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We investigate systematic gender differences in students&amp;rsquo; referral for intellectual giftedness assessments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Earth is Not Flat: A New World of High-Dimensional Peer Effects</title>
      <link>https://asallin.github.io/publication/hdpx/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asallin.github.io/publication/hdpx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The majority of recent peer-effect studies in education have focused on the effect of one particular type of peers on classmates. This view fails to take into account the reality that peer effects are heterogeneous for students with different characteristics, and that there are at least as many peer effect functions as there are types of peers. In this paper, we develop a general empirical framework that accounts for systematic interactions between peer types and nonlinearities of peer effects. We use machine-learning methods to (i) understand which dimensions of peer characteristics are the most predictive of academic success, (ii) estimate high-dimensional peer effects functions, and (iii) investigate performance-improving classroom allocation through policy-relevant simulations. First, we find that students&amp;rsquo; own characteristics are the most predictive of academic success, and that the most predictive peer effects are generated by students with special needs, low-achieving students, and male students. Second, we show that peer effects traditionally reported by the literature likely miss important nonlinearities in the distribution of peer proportions. Third, we determine that classroom compositions that are the most balanced in students&amp;rsquo; characteristics are the best ways to reach maximal aggregated school performance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High-Ability Influencers? The Heterogeneous Effects of Gifted Classmates</title>
      <link>https://asallin.github.io/publication/gifted/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asallin.github.io/publication/gifted/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We study the causal impact of intellectually gifted students on their nongifted classmates’ school achievement, enrollment in post-compulsory education, and occupational choices. Using student-level administrative and psychological data, we find a positive effect of exposure to gifted students on peers’ school achievement in both math and language. This impact is heterogeneous. Larger effects are observed among male students and high achievers; female students benefit primarily from female gifted students; effects are driven by gifted students not diagnosed with emotional or behavioral disorders. Exposure to gifted students increases the likelihood of choosing a selective academic track and occupations in STEM fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Media coverage: the St. Galler &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tagblatt.ch/leben/hochbegabung-begabte-jugendliche-befeuern-die-leistung-der-ganzen-klasse-jedenfalls-wenn-es-maedchen-sind-ld.2148101&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tagblatt&lt;/a&gt; and interview on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=db84CGAyF_4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Youtube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating returns to special education: combining machine learning and text analysis to address confounding</title>
      <link>https://asallin.github.io/publication/jmp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://asallin.github.io/publication/jmp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While the number of students with identified special needs is increasing in developed countries, there is little empirical evidence on academic and labor market returns to special education. By leveraging unique insights into the special education placement process through written individual psychological records, I present results from the first ever study to examine short- and long-term returns to special education programs with causal machine learning and computational text analysis methods. I find that special education programs in inclusive settings have positive returns on academic performance in math and language as well as on employment and wages. Moreover, I uncover a positive effect of inclusive special education programs in comparison to segregated programs, and I find that students with emotional or behavioral problems and nonnative students benefit more from segregation than the other students. Finally, I deliver optimal placement rules that increase overall returns for students with special needs and lower special education costs. These placement rules would reallocate most students with special needs from segregation to inclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
